Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department. Maury Holland papers, 1948-1959 RL.00711
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department. Maury Holland papers
1948-1959
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00711
1179
1.2 Linear Feet
750 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Maury (C. Maurice) Holland (1896-1974) was a Vaudeville and Broadway actor before joining the JWT New York Office's Radio and Television Department in 1936 to direct radio and television programs for the agency. Collection includes scripts for and copies of outgoing memoranda regarding content and format of television programs and advertisements, as well as budget and production information. Programs include Bat Masterson, Jackie Gleason Show, Kraft Television Theatre, Naked City and The Price is Right. Actors and writers represented in the collection include J.P. McEvoy, Jackie Gleason, Milton Berle, Mitch Miller and Moura Budberg. Advertisers include the Advertising Council, Coldene, Kraft, Quaker Oats and Rinso. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department. Maury Holland papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) was founded in New York in 1864 and is one of the world's oldest and largest advertising firms.
Maury (C. Maurice) Holland was a vaudevillian and Broadway actor (1920s) who worked for Columbia in both silent films and talkie shorts (1930s) and then joined the JWT New York Office's Radio and Television Department in 1936 to direct radio shows for the agency. The Radio/TV Department was responsible for creating and working with radio and television programs to advertise JWT client products. Among other programs, Holland directed Kraft Television Theatre, a live anthology drama series on NBC, from 1948 to the show's cancellation in 1958. He died Nov. 14, 1974 in Greenwich, Conn.
Collection Overview
Collection includes scripts for and copies of outgoing memoranda regarding content and format of television programs and advertisements, as well as budget and production information. Programs include Bat Masterson, Jackie Gleason Show, Kraft Television Theatre, Naked City and The Price is Right. Actors and writers represented in the collection include J.P. McEvoy, Jackie Gleason, Milton Berle, Mitch Miller and Moura Budberg. Advertisers include the Advertising Council, Coldene, Kraft, Quaker Oats and Rinso. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
J. Walter Thompson Company. 16mm as-broadcast scripts
J. Walter Thompson Company. Carroll Carroll papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department records
Scripts (documents); Memoranda; Advertising executives -- United States; Television advertising -- United States; Advertising -- History; Television plays, American; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States; Comedians -- United States; Television personalities -- United States; Television programs -- United States; Masterson, Bat, 1853-1921; Kraft Foods Company; Quaker Oats Company; National Broadcasting Company, Inc.; Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; Advertising Council; Gleason, Jackie, 1916-1987; Berle, Milton; J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office; Holland, Maury; J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; J. Walter Thompson Company
- Maury Holland papers, 1949-1959; 1
  - Advertising Council--Confidence in a Growing America campaign, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Bat Masterson, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Budgets, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Chicago correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Chicago correspondence--Naked City, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Coldene, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
  - East coast production bills, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Folios, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - J.P. (Joseph Patrick) McEvoy, 1959 (Box 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    J.P. (Joseph Patrick) McEvoy (1897-1958); American author who contributed to popular magazines such as Saturday Evening Post and Reader's Digest; playwright for Ziegfield Follies and Broadway; novelist whose works were adapted into the Show Girl series of movies by Hollywood; creator of the Dixie Dugan comic series. Correspondence in folder concerns McEvoy's scripts adapted for television, between Holland and Mrs. Peggy McEvoy.
  - Jackie Gleason A-B (as broadcast) scripts, 1958-1959; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Jackie Gleason Show, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - John Crosby clippings, 1949 (Box 2)
    John Crosby (1912-1991); American journalist, columnist, radio and television critic, television panel host, writer of suspense novels.
  - Kraft clippings, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Kraft show, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Kraft summer budget, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Kraft television, 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Milton Berle, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Mitch Miller, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Most Blessed Woman releases, 1957-1958; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Moura Budberg correspondence, 1957 (Box 2)
    (Baroness) Moura Budberg (Maria Ignatievna Budberg; 1891-1974) was a Russian-born translator, writer and reputed double agent spy for Britain and the Soviet Union. Longtime association with literary figures including Maxim Gorky and H.G. Wells.
  - Naked City, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - NBC correspondence, 1958 (Box 2)
  - NBC Network Production Facilities, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Price is Right, 1958; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Price is Right commercials, 1958; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Quaker Oats commercials, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Returned scripts, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Review of Kraft Television, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Rinso Blue, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Stripe toothpaste commercial, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Talent associates, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Teletypes, 1958 (Box 3)